Jasper McLevy Collection
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
Jasper McLevy Collection
1900-1962
McLevy, Jasper
BHC-MSS 0002
35 l ft. 12 manuscript boxes, 8 record cartons, 13 oversized boxes
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
The Jasper McLevy Collection represents the professional and public life of Jasper McLevy, Bridgeport's socialist mayor from 1933-1957. It holds records from his administration, documentation from the Socialist Party of Bridgeport including minute books and account books, and personal scrapbooks compiled by McLevy, as well as speeches and additional material.
Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Biography
Jasper McLevy (March 27, 1878-November 20, 1962) served as the mayor of Bridgeport, Connecticut from 1933 to 1957. The city's first socialist mayor, he is best remembered for helping to resolve the city's bankruptcy, on the site inspections, and keeping a tight purse string, as well as weeding out the corruption of the earlier mayors of the city. To many in the city, he was simply known by his first name, Jasper.
McLevy was the son of Scottish immigrants, and the oldest of nine children. He began to work with his father in the roofing trade after a stint of factory jobs prior to his leaving the eighth grade. His interest in Socialism came from reading the book Looking Backward by Edward Bellamy, and would soon see him make a large number of attempts at public office. He ran for the Connecticut General Assembly as a socialist in 1902, and that was followed by twenty more unsuccessful campaigns for various public offices. It took nine campaigns for him to be elected mayor of Bridgeport, and these campaigns frequently featured him on a soapbox.
Small successes prior to his election in 1933 did exist though. In 1903 he helped to get a petition passed that funded free textbooks for elementary school children in the city. He also did organization work for the Central Labor Union, and became the International President of the Slate and Tile Roofer's Union.
These activities helped elect him to the office of mayor in 1933, following the resignation of Mayor Buckingham and the ensuing contest between James L. Dunn, President of the Common Council, and McLevy. The tally was in McLevy's favor with 22,445 votes, a lead of about 6,000 over Dunn.
McLevy inherited a city wide debt upon coming into office, a combination of the 1929 stock market crash and poor management by the city afterwards. That the federal government assumed the city's debt about eight days after McLevy was elected helped significantly. His administration was noted for penny pinching during McLevy's time in office. Frequently McLevy's work day involved his going into his office for an hour in the morning and in the afternoon, and spending the rest of the day elsewhere in Bridgeport with those he represented.
Under his tenure, McLevy became known for being out in the field, for his fiscal restraint, and generally focusing on the details of managing the city. He helped to bring the civil service to Bridgeport, build miles of esplanades for the Park City, spent federal relief money carefully, maintained low taxes, and helped to overhaul Bridgeport's sewer system channeling waste to dedicated plants rather than out into the Long Island Sound. Bridgeport saw four federal housing projects built under McLevy's administration, including the later infamous Father Panik Village which was built as part of a "slum clearance" project.
His approach to running the city was not without criticism. The inaccurate, but often told story of McLevy declaring "God put the show there, let Him take it away" reflects the fact that his hold on the city purse strings was sometimes too tight. Beyond snow removal, he objected to an extra $4,500 for a dedicated full-time school physician, and later in his career, was caught up in a fight with city firefighters who wanted better conditions and more pay - a surprise for a man who was international president of a trade union. Critiques increased as McLevy's tenure grew longer. One notable one came as the city expanded - new residents in newly developed areas were not receiving the same fire, police, and sewer service as older parts of the city. Downtown began to show its age, and there was no spending dedicated to improve it.
Come 1955 the Bridgeport Democrats ran Samuel Tedesco against McLevy. While McLevy remained mayor for two more years, Tedesco unseated him in 1957. McLevy campaigned for reelection afterwards, and he only stopped his engagement when he suffered a stroke in 1960.
Beyond his impact as mayor of Bridgeport, McLevy was also a part of the Socialist Party both in Connecticut and nationally. He helped get three socialists into the state senate, and two representatives in Hartford come 1934. Some critics viewed McLevy and others as being so-called Old Guard Socialists who only appeared to adhere to party principles but failed to act on them. This tension came to a head at the Detroit Convention of the Socialist Party in 1934. The Declaration of Principles, which had a more radical bent, was adopted at this time. Members that voted against the declaration formed the Social Democratic Federation, which McLevy then joined, creating friction with party loyalists. In 1938 briefly, and then permanently in 1950, McLevy and the Connecticut Socialists left the National Party. McLevy's socialism was decidedly low key, and his work primarily focused on reform.
Much of McLevy's life outside of politics remained private to the point of being mostly hidden from the public. There is little known about his first wife, Mary Flynn. He married his second wife, Vida Stearns, in 1929, but this information remained unknown for five years until The Herald found the records in the Office of Vital Statistics. Stearns herself was an artist, and the two had a farm in Washington, Connecticut, which served as their shared home. According to rumor, the real reason the two lived apart was because Stearn's father objected to a perceived abandonment of socialist principles by McLevy, but this information was never remarked upon by either. In their later years, they had two collies, both named Lassie, who were photographed frequently with McLevy, along with a cat named Peter.
Jasper McLevy died on November 19, 1962. His honesty in office was constantly remarked upon, as was the frugality of his tenure.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Jasper McLevy collection primarily provides an overview of Jasper McLevy's professional and political life, with an emphasis on his time as the mayor of Bridgeport and his association with socialism.
Correspondence, mayoral files, and related material cover the personal papers of McLevy, starting in 1919 and ending in 1962. The vast majority of the contents relate to his political and public life, but additional material towards the end of the series addresses his personal life and includes correspondence with his second wife Vida Stearns and information about their farm.
The Socialist Party of Bridgeport series primarily contains the minute books of the Socialist Party of Bridgeport, as well as several account books, offering insight into the functions and day to day events of the party at the time. Other material focuses on their activity and campaigns they have been involved in, including platforms, a scrapbook of newspaper advertisements, and campaign literature.
The material in the speeches series features drafts and finalized press releases of various speeches given by McLevy over the years.
Printed material documents the various functions that McLevy attended or else was invited to, showing the scope of his involvement with the city, as well as organizations at the state and national level.
Scrapbooks are curated by McLevy himself, and demonstrate how he viewed himself. Their date range provides a broad overview of his career in the public eye.
Clippings are arranged by rough chronological order when possible. However many folders are undated, due to the delicate nature of the clippings. They may yet undergo preservation work.
3d items are primarily awards given to McLevy.
The two boxes at the end of unprocessed material contain items that need treatment, but are likely unable to be attended to in the near future.
Arrangement
In 2010, an inventory and initial processing of the Jasper McLevy papers were begun by Robert G. Marshall, who mainly organized the correspondence, mayoral files, and related material files. Processing was begun again in 2017 by Meghan Rinn who completed the project.
The Jasper McLevy Papers are arranged into six series, based primary on format. They are correspondence, mayoral files, and related material; Socialist Party of Bridgeport; Speeches; Printed Material; Scrapbooks; Clippings; 3D items; and unprocessed material.
Note that the contents of boxes 19 through 21 were found near the end of processing. A decision was made not to integrate them into the existing scrapbook boxes primarily because these scrapbooks are in poorer condition than the others, and it was safer to keep them apart.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
McLevy, Jasper, 1878-1962; Socialist Party of the United States of America; Connecticut - Bridgeport; Politicians - Connecticut - Bridgeport - Biography; Socialism - United States - History - 20th Century
- Series I, Correspondence, mayoral files, and related material
  - Correspondence, mayoral files, and related material, 1919-1933 (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
  - Correspondence, mayoral files, and related material, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 1-9)
  - Correspondence, mayoral files, and related material, 1936-1939 (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
  - Correspondence, mayoral files, and related material, 1940-1953 (Box 4, Folder 1-15)
  - Correspondence, mayoral files, and related material, 1954-1962 (Box 5, Folder 1-11)
  - Charter amendments to the City of Bridgeport, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Survey and Recommendations of the Hartford Police Department, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Narrative, Wheeler property for prop. Civic Center, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Wheeler Mansion, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Honorary degree from Wesleyan, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Vida Stearns, early correspondence, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Mrs. McLevy’s lectures, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Income tax, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence re: secret marriage, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - McLevy farm documents, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Obituaries, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Greeting cards, 1920s-1960 (Box 7, Folder 5-8)
  - Political cartoons of McLevy, 1947-1957 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - National cyclopedia of American Biography portrait of McLevy, signed, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, McLevy and other officials, 1941-1970s (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Portraits of McLevy, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Photographs of McLevy from Unknown Scrapbook, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Photographs, Construction of Bridgeport Firehouse #16, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Photographs, Dorthoy Secor and Audubon J. Secor, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Other photographs, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Negatives, McLevy, undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Series II, Speeches
  - Speeches, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 1-21)
  - Various short topic essays, undated (Box 8, Folder 22)
- Series III, Socialist Party of Bridgeport
  - Socialist Party of Bridgeport minutes, 1900-1920 (Box 9, Folder 1-6)
  - Socialist Party of Bridgeport minutes, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Socialist Party of America Financial Secretary’s Ledger, c., 1908 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Socialist Party of Bridgeport combination account book, 1911-1930 (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
  - Additional socialist party materials including ballots, 1912-1936 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Declaration of Principles, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - In Answer to Devere Allen's Alleged Truth about New York: by James ONeal, March, 1936; Rules, minutes of National Convention of Democratic Socialists, May 29-31, 1937; List of bills sponsored by the Socialist Party of Connecticut, 1939p; Hartford's Tammany Hall and Invisible Government" by Bellani Trombley, undated, 1936-1939 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Socialist Party newspaper advertising scrapbook, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Socialist party publications and advertising, 1930-1959 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Socialist Party platforms, 1938-1946 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Socialist Party banquet programs, 1939-1942 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - McLevy Mayoral Campaign literature, 1939-1945 (Box 11, Folder 8-10)
  - History of the Socialist Party in Connecticut Integrated with the National Socialist Party by Victory E. Muniec, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Socialism and women: the Bridgeport Experience, by Henry H. Barnard, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, socialists, 1920-1969 (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Series IV, Printed material
  - Programs, 1934-1960 (Box 12, Folder 1-5)
- Series V, Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook, 1933-1934 (Box 13, Folder 1-3)
  - Scrapbook, 1934-1935 (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
  - Scrapbook, 1935-1937 (Box 15, Folder 1-3)
  - Scrapbook, 1937-1960 (Box 16, Folder 1-3)
  - Scrapbook, 1959-1970s (Box 17, Folder 1-3)
  - Socialist party scrapbook, 1934-1941 (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
  - Scrapbook, Socialist party, 1905-1910 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1929-1932 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1937-1955 (Box 20, Folder 1-3)
  - Scrapbook, 1956 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, Awards to Mc Levy, 1950-1959 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, group photos and testimonials, 1950-1959 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, personal and untitled, undated (Box 21, Folder 4)
- Series VI, Clippings
  - Clippings, 1934 (Box 22, Folder 1-11)
  - Clippings, 1935-1938 (Box 23, Folder 1-14)
  - Clippings, 1938-1939 (Box 24, Folder 1-10)
  - Clipping, 1940-1949 (Box 25, Folder 1-8)
  - Clippings, 1950-1954 (Box 26, Folder 1-10)
  - Clippings, Barnum Festival, 1953-1954 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, Barnum Festival, 1955-1957 (Box 27, Folder 1-3)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 27, Folder 4-14)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 28, Folder 1-12)
  - Newspapers, 1937-1960 (Box 29, Folder 1-9)
- Series VII, 3-d items and oversized material
  - Cap, gown, and honorary degree from Wesleyan University, 1941 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Bridgeport Municipal Airport sign, undated (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Recognition award from YMCA Industrial Recreation council, 1960 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Legion of Valor recognition award, 1935 (Box 31, Folder 3)
- Series VII, Unprocessed material
  - Two wooden boxes for documents bearing McLevy’s name on the spine. Due to acidic nature, these spines will be sawed off and put in safe housing, and the boxes themselves discarded, undated (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - A scroll and additional photographs that are curled up and in need of treatment, undated (Box 33, Folder 1)
- Accrual, March 2018
  - Page 1 biography, revised to April 7, 1962 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Campaigns, 1962 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Administration, 1962 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Socialist splits, 1962 (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Soapbox, 8 takes, 1962 (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Inspected city jobs, 1962 (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - Housing plan, 1962 (Box 34, Folder 7)
- Accrual, August 2018
  - Award from Bridgeport Brass Company Quarter Central Club to McLevy, 1954 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Emancipation award to McLevy, 1954 (Box 35, Folder 2)